Register of the Alexander H. Buchman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander H. Buchman papers
1920-2003
84075
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 10 envelopes, 5 motion picture film reels, 2 videocassettes, 14 slides, 6 sound cassettes (2.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, police reports, printed matter, motion picture film, still photographs, and slides relating to Leon Trotsky and Trotskyism, especially in China and the United States, to the Trotskyist C. Frank Glass, and to Rayna Prohme, revolutionary American journalist in China.
Buchman, Alexander H., 1911-2003.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all motion picture material in this collection are available for immediate access. To access sound recordings or video recordings, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1911 Born, Cleveland, Ohio
1933 Received degree in aeronautical engineering from Case School of Applied Science
1933-1939 Lived in Shanghai, China
1939-1940 Lived in Cayoacan, Mexico; served as Leon Trotsky's bodyguard
2003 Died, Los Angeles, California
Scope and Content of Collection
The Alexander H. Buchman papers document Buchman's activities as an amateur photographer living in Shanghai, China and Coyoacan, Mexico, and his relationship with Leon Trotsky. The collection includes film and photographs of Leon Trotsky and members of his entourage, including his wife, Natalia Sedova, Diego Rivera, and others, in Coyoacan, Mexico between 1939 and 1940. Buchman’s photographs of Shanghai and other areas of China include scenes of the bombing of Shanghai in 1937 and executions of leftists in China between 1927 and 1932. The collection also includes a sound recording of a telephone address to followers in the United States made by Trotsky from Mexico in 1938.
Also among Buchman’s papers is correspondence with friends and colleagues who shared his interest in the history of Trotskyism, including Baruch Hirson, Susan Weissman, and Trotsky’s grandson, Esteban Volkov.
Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.; Shanghai (China); Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945.; Communism--United States.; Communism--China.; Glass, C. Frank (Cecil Frank), 1901-1988.; Fourth International.; China--Pictorial works.; Prohme, Rayna, -1927.; Americans--China.; Audiotapes.; Video tapes.; Motion pictures.; Slides (Photography)
- Biographical File, 1920-2002
  - Articles about Alexander Buchman, 2001 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Identification documents, photocopies, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Jokes collected by Alexander Buchman, 2002 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance reports and interview transcripts, with related correspondence, 1920-2000 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence, 1937-2003
  - Unidentified, 2001 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - The China Leprosy Association/Foundation, 1988 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Columbia University Press [see: Wang, Fanxi]
  - Crook, David, 1988-1996 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Durdin, Tillman, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Epstein, Israel, 1998 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Glotzer, Albert, 1990-1998 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Gould, Randall [see: Subject File/Agnes Smedley], 1988
  - Grunefeld, A. Tom, 1993 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Hirson, Baruch, 1991-1999 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Hirson, Yael, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Hoover Institution Library & Archives, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Hunt, Sam, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Isaacs, Harold and Viola, 1975, 1984-1986, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Jan Frankel search correspondence, 1937, 1986-1997 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Knodel, Arthur, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 1: 18, 2: 1)
  - MacKinnon, Stephen [see: Subject File/Agnes Smedley], 1988
  - Marcopoulos, George, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Messmer, Matthias, 2003 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Moustakis, Elizabeth, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Rand, Peter, 1989-1998 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Rosholt, Malcolm, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Turnbull, Emily (Prometheus Research Library) [see also: Hunt, Sam], 1988-1989, 1996-2001 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Volkov, Esteban, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Wang, Fanxi, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Wang, Y. Y., 2000-2001 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Weissman, Susan, 1988-2000 (Box-folder 2: 11-13)
- Writings by Others, 1973-1994
  - Benton, Gregor, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Hirson, Baruch, 1973-1988 (Box-folder 2: 15, 3: 1-2)
  - Kessler, Ralph, 1988 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Knodel, Arthur and Baruch Hirson, circa 1990 (Box-folder 3: 4-6)
  - Pantsov, Alexander, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Petras, James, circa 1991 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Wang, Fanxi, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Weissman, Susan, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Conferences File, 1989-1993
  - "International Trotsky Symposium,", 1989-1993 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - "Trotsky in Cardenas' Mexico: 1937-1987" colloquium, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- Subject File, 1926-1998
  - Agnes Smedley, 1927-1988 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Esteban Volkov, 1940-1990 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Irving Weissman, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Leon Trotsky, 1926-1998 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Photographs and Slides, 1927-1945
  - Approximately 750 contact prints of Leon Trotsky and members of his entourage in Coyoacan, Mexico, circa 1939-1940 (Envelope A-C)
  - 12 enlarged prints of Leon Trotsky in Coyoacan, Mexico, circa 1939-1940 (Envelope D)
  - 6 enlarged prints of Leon Trotsky with his wife and members of his entourage in Coyoacan, Mexico, circa 1939-1940 (Envelope E)
  - 14 enlarged prints of members of the entourage of Leon Trotsky in Coyoacan, Mexico, circa 1939-1940 (Envelope F)
  - 3 enlarged prints, including 2 of Diego Rivera in Coyoacan, Mexico, and 1 of a painting by Rivera, circa 1939-1940 (Envelope G)
  - 40 prints of executions of leftists in China, circa 1927-1932 (Envelope H)
  - 14 color slides of Leon Trotsky in Mexico, circa 1939-1940 (Slide cabinet)
  - 2 copies of one print and negative depicting the core members of the provisional central committee of the Communist League of China (Trotskyist opposition), 1936 (Envelope I)
  - 19 prints depicting members of the Communist League of China and atrocities in the Wuhan area; 1 print depicting Lunghua Civilian Assembly Center, 1923-1945 (Envelope J)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes a print of Agnes Smedley with others, 1932 or 1933.
- Sound Recordings, 1938-1939, 1988-1989 (Cassette cabinet)
  - "Trotsky Speech from Mexico to NYC. Oct. 18 1938. 16 min. With Intro," sound cassette
  - "Esteban Volkov San Francisco Speech, Aug. 6 1988. Intro by Paul Siegel," sound cassette
  - "Memorial Service for Milt Genecin San Francisco February 5, 1989," sound cassette
  - "Memorial Service for Frank Glass Los Angeles California 4/23/88," sound cassette, 1988
  - "L. Trotsky Speech 10-18-39 on 10th Anniv. of U.S. Left Opposition," sound cassette, undated
  - "Portraits of USSR - KPFK Los Angeles Interview with Sieva Volkov 02/18/88," sound cassette, 1988
- Videorecordings, 1937-1940
  - Film reels, 1937-1940 (Film shelf)
    - Leon Trotsky and members of his entourage in Coyoacan, Mexico, 16 mm print, silent, circa 1939-1940 (Reel 1-2)
      Access
      Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 84075_f_0007971.
    - Street scenes in Shanghai, China, 16 mm print, silent, circa 1938-1939 (Reel 3)
      Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 84075_f_0010513.
      Depicts the foreign presence in Shanghai. Opening shots show U.S.S. Augusta leaving Shanghai. Other scenes show French, British, American (4th Marines), and Shanghai Municipal Police.
    - Bombing of Shanghai during the Sino-Japanese War, 16 mm print, black & white, silent, 1937 (Reel 4)
      Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 84075_f_0010530.
      Primarily scenes on or near the Shanghai Bund on "Bloody Saturday," August 14, 1939, when Chinese aircraft tried to bomb the Japanese cruiser Idzumo but instead bombed Nanking Road and the Bund, and Nanking Road at the New World Entertainment Centre.
    - Foreign warships and troops in Shanghai, China, 16 mm print, black & white, silent, circa 1937-1939 (Reel 5)
      Use copy available on-site for immediate use. Use copy reference number: 84075_f_0010531.
      Scenes of poverty, life on the streets, the dispossessed, refugees. Shanghai, 1938-1939.
  - Videocassettes (U-matic, 3/4"), undated (Tape cabinet)
    - "China Footage Part 1" (copy of film reel 3)
    - "China Footage Part 2" (copy of film reels 4 and 5)
- Printed Matter, 1927-2003
  - "Against the Current,", 1940 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Against the Current, 2001 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - The Catholic Worker, 2003 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - The China Connection, 2001 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Christianity's Social Record, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - "Daybreak,", 1939 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - "Fifth Conference on Leon Trotsky Highlights the Relevance of His Work,", 1999 (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Form letters, 1995 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Heritage, 2003 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Living Age, circa 1930-1940 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1927, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 4: 17)
  - "Photos by Rewi Alley,", 1987 (Box-folder 4: 18)
  - Publisher newsletters, 1986-2002 (Box-folder 4: 19)
  - Shanghai city guide, incomplete photocopy, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 20)